[Music]
Jordan Peterson has become hugely
successful what do you make of the
phenomena why do you think he's become
so successful now there is a drought of
authenticity and courage and Peterson
has found that hunger and he's tapped
into it and I'm I admire his ability to
detect it and to speak to it plainly in
a way that it resonates with I did we
were on a panel together in Vancouver
and I watched his talk and he described
his own surprise at how effective his
message had been and he basically said
that if he had outlined his message as
the core of a business model that it
would have looked laughable to him and
that he was as shocked as anybody that
people are resonating with it but when
when you live in a world that is as full
of crap as the world we live in where
people are advertising bullshit to you
from the moment you get up to the moment
you go to sleep and then somebody
finally tells you some truth that you
need to hear it's a relief it's a relief
just to know that there's some channel
that isn't compromised by nonsense and
he I don't think he's the only one
speaking truthfully but I think he is
speaking from the heart
and people know it I think that he
grasps directly the fact that human
beings can only actually make sense of
the world by virtue of communication
with other human beings and this is all
about the notion of admixture that one
must have a mixture of of love I mean he
uses the mythopoetic to make sense the
order order and chaos the way or the
Daoist way is the alchemical admixture
of order and chaos and that's it like
that's how you do it
and so if you
you biased towards orderliness you find
yourself in a rigid non-adaptive
non creative non exploratory framework
which will die because the world changes
if you bias towards chaos you you eat
your young and evaporate which also
theis for obvious reasons and the key is
to actually enable these things to be in
relationship with each other and vital
healthy relationship with each other and
I think that's in some sense the essence
of what he's focusing on and instead of
the core what he's acting about he's
very easy to work with as his voice is
an instrument because he speaks very
deliberately and sonorous ly and
rhythmically anyway he actually speaks
in in a kind of form of rhythmic poetry
sometimes he is actually rapid
Peterson's words plus low Phi hip-hop
equals jbp way
at first it's like oh it's a novelty
thing and then I kind of listen to him
is like no it's not a novelty thing this
is actually really good yeah that's been
that's been the reaction all over I
think that was Peterson's reaction he
was instantly like thought this was
gonna be silly and was amusing it was
like oh this is actually awful and I
were now essentially proving useful and
that's generally interesting that you
say as well that Peterson has a very
musical or a very performative aspect to
his speech because he talks about
performing that performance or aligning
yourself with the truth and if you're
aligning yourself with the logos of the
creative principle you would expect to
be for that to have an effect on your
actual performance but he feels like a
very embodied speaker when he's onstage
like he's fully inhabiting the stories
that he's that he's telling and that
that performative aspect of it is seems
to me at least also related to what he's
talking about the logo of something
incarnated more in your life and
incarnate and more in your in your being
yes and watching him become that over
the years because he was not always as
as confident and able to just now you
know you free stars right
he's his whole career yes all careers
really reminded me of it's very $0.50
for example got big off the back of
drama there was created drama you know
beefs with other rappers and being shot
13 times and all this stuff which draws
people into the story
but then he had this huge body of work
and that kept people there Peterson did
this Peterson had these public dramas
and that brought people to him but then
when they got to him they there was this
huge body of work for them to get sort
of lost and immersed in it Peterson has
some kind of drama like every week at
this point he's like the ultimate sort
of contemporary battle rapper he's at
war with all sorts of people at all
times and it's brilliant very
interesting and if you're inside you
know if you're a rap fan or if you're
what would you call if you're a
intellectual dark whatever the hell it
is fat it's like this guy's getting
incredible beefs every week right and
there's a new sort of supervillain to
root against every week three guards to
him or if you're on his site or not you
know it's the whole thing's very
entertaining but then he pulls you in
and then there's all this meaning and
this huge body of work
[Music]
but he's quite new on this light if you
watch him like 15 years ago it was a bit
awkward and sort of he was very charming
and he knew what he was talking about
but the absolute fucking beast that he
has become as a performance creature who
can now just rock up at an amphitheater
and just like freestyle the new to our
lecture off the top of his head and he's
very into not repeating himself too much
in his lake you go see a standard
comedian you'll see pretty much the same
set every week for like a year or
something right he won't do that he's
more like a very good DJ you know he has
all these yes like a fistful of things
that you know his works together and
they're linked and he can take on these
different journeys but depending on
who's in the room and where he is he
will create a new and transformative
always experience where it where is his
insight coming from and so we talking to
you when you were describing hey you
almost sound a little bit like Jordan
pieces I mean in the sense of yeah I
mean if I had to describe my worldview
in a nutshell it would be sort of a
Neoplatonic so there was a Neoplatonic
stoic mystic Chryst agnostic so the idea
of Neoplatonic I believe it I have
always just sort of felt like there is a
realm of ideal forms
stoic do the suck it up fat kid and do
the hard thing 100% Gnostic there is a
certain ineffable experience of being
and then the mystic Christic is some
some reflection on the judeo-christian
Western tradition but nothing to do with
2,000 years of bureaucratic
administration and everything to do with
what is nominally the metaphor of Kairos
and Chronos the intersection of kind of
sacred and profane time in human form so
in that respect yeah I would track with
with Peterson my sense is for me my you
know gnosis or understanding has come
from ex ptosis has come from peak
experiences and my sense for him at
least as he shares what he does of his
life has come from catharsis has come
from the suffering it's come from
battling depressions come from staring
the abyss
the face versus the view from the summit
and those are ideally come full circle
and reinforce each other but if I had to
sort of delineate maybe where's his
transmission anchoring from it's maybe a
little bit more the staring the abyss
and and and surviving it then then
calling out coordinates from the
mountaintop the most important thing
from me quite apart from his work with
these stories modernist was as you say
his investigation into the Bible and
I've always been fascinated although I'm
an atheist I'm always been fascinated by
the power of the biblical stories I
often found myself looking at these huge
cathedrals and churches that sprouted up
all over Europe you know and and asked
myself well what's that about you know
why was this story so powerful I mean
yeah it's the defense against death if
you want to be cynical but hey you know
it could be lots of other stories you
know why is this one so unbelievably
powerful and what does it mean for it to
be so powerful and pieces I think
brilliantly answers that question in the
biblical lectures he's done and he
really changed me those lectures who
genuinely did I think changed the way I
lived my life because he came to this
very very important conclusion which I'm
pretty convinced by I don't think I'm
ever 100% convinced about anything but
I'm very convinced by his idea as I've
someone who's suffered depression and
depression is like a crisis of meaning
in your the worst thing about depression
is not about being miserable being
having a life that seems utterly
meaningless and that's why it's such
torment and Petersons in a way tries to
answer the question how do we as an
individual that's a bit of a paradox how
do i as an individual acquire meaning
because meaning is the most important
thing any of us could have you know
there's meaning as it you know if you
don't know and yet no one can quite say
what meaning is which i think is
interesting in itself you know one says
well I want a sense of meaning what is a
sense of me what is meaning and Peterson
I think it knowledge is that mystery but
also it says well you know if you want a
sense of meaning it's not about just
doing what you want it's not about just
following your bliss as Joseph Campbell
would be or having a much fun as
possible or or even necessarily being
happy no absolutely no not necessarily
being happy it's there were more
important things than being happy and
and I've also found that to be true in
my life when Adam and Matt invited me to
do that podcast we were all someone who
similar to the two of you I believe was
starting to track Peterson and not just
Jordan Peterson and what he was saying
but also the ripples he was having a
culture the absolute phenomenon and
explosion of attention that was
happening around him in the media and
started kind of watching him reading him
with an open mind my experience was an
open mind like oh I resonate with that I
love always bringing Carl Jung and
Joseph Campbell and archetypal
dimensions to his thinking like how he's
kind of kicking the left a little bit
and calling them on some of their
problematic thinking and then watching
this kind of phenomenon from the left or
the far left with people just with
extraordinary levels of anger and fear
and distrust and kind of the the
difference in that experience of my own
and some of our experiences of Peterson
and then watching a lot of friends who
are on the far left
having radically different experience
and perception of who he is and what
he's bringing and was really just
curious about that and it it seems like
similar to some of the stuff you've been
doing with rebel wisdom and as a I mean
you're training as a psychologist we do
a lot of work with with psychology as
well when there's a huge reactivity to
something there's always something
interesting going on behind it and it
sort of makes you inquire it's like okay
what is what are people reacting to yes
whether you love them or hate them it's
that equal proportion of intensity and
whenever that's there it's what's kind
of called a complex complex is a
is a psychological and I think young
would say it like it can be a autonomous
and autonomous complex is it's not part
of the ego it's so deep-rooted and it's
my opinion it's a collective complex in
the collective unconscious it's like
everyone on the right thinks everyone on
the left is a Stalinist and everyone
everyone on the right thinks everyone
everyone the left thinks everyone the
right is a Nazi and there's this
polarization happening where people like
like Peterson who are trying to carve
out I would say not non-political but a
kind of a position that's lateral to
politics that's more in the
psychological domain to ask people to
look at themselves as individuals to
question the extent to which they're
projecting their shadow on to the other
which until we can resolve issues on
that level it's gonna be very difficult
to resolve these political disagreements
and so that's one of the main reasons
that I've found myself so interested in
what Peterson is saying he's shifting
the level of the conversation of trying
to at least I was so excited to see
Jordan Peterson erupted onto the stage
and I know you had particularly part in
that there is a culture war that is in
bright precedence I mean we are in the
middle of a culture war there's a
polarization and Jordan Peterson is
standing in the middle as a lightning
rod taking all the projections from both
sides he clearly sees the postmodern
ideology and it is an ideology it's a
system of beliefs and values that will
not lead us to the promised land it is
it is problematic it leads us into a
swamp with no exit it is not sustainable
he sees it very clearly and in my
opinion he sees it from a modern
perspective very brilliant modern
perspective he sees and he has a depth
because of his understanding of Carl
Jung and his own work in psychology the
field of psychology that is deeper than
most people so people are drawn to that
depth he sees something much deeper then
other people are seeing right now we had
had we'd never met one another um I knew
actually very little about Jordan
Peterson has written work he knew pretty
little about mine and we were just told
sit down and shoot and we had no idea
where we were going so he just started
talking
so why the most Rinna's hemisphere and
he just went from there but what I felt
was here was you know a super
intelligent man who had wide-ranging
interests in psychology philosophy and
didn't rule out a spiritual angle to
things and I don't think that I would an
end in the film I in that clip I think
he probably comes out that there are
aspects of what Jordan was saying that I
was getting well yes but so I didn't
entirely kind of not a Peter Peter
Sounion but I do have a huge respect for
him and we had a great conversation and
we were proposing to do more what do you
make of the sort of the criticisms as
often he's described as a fraud or a
charlatan in some of the the media
coverage but when you watch the
interview with yourself I mean that's
that's a very high-level conversation
the idea of him as a fraud or a
charlatan just seems kind of bizarre
it's it's outrageous it's it's
disrespectful its dismissive and it's
entirely typical of blinkered liberalism
he you can disagree with him about many
things and I would disagree with him
about a number of things but to say that
is just to show how could you
he's clearly an extraordinary man and I
never Charlotte what does that mean I
think what strikes people is that he was
relatively unknown and then he became
known but that's what life isn't it
doesn't prove for a Sharla's yeah I mean
a lot of this sounds quite Jordan Peters
and esque
what's your attitude Jordan Peterson
yeah I mean I I'm glad he's out there
and I think there are you know I mean I
think at a minimum there's sort of three
different jordan Peterson's you know
there's Jordan Peterson the analyst and
academic which virtually nobody ever
heard of there's Jordan Peterson the
kind of contrary in public intellectual
which sort of you know kicked off in
2016 and then there's sort of Jordan
Peterson sort of raw shot and blot for
the culture wars of which both left and
right wildly distort who he is what he's
saying and what it and what it means for
them and so we get we get the the second
and the third ones completely mixed
although the first one you know
University of Toronto and hop near
former Harvard professors the one that
gives the credibility and the weight to
the other two dialogues so in that
respect I think as I what I imagined him
to be as an actual man is a pretty high
integrity principled person who likes to
think for himself and likes to speak not
just truth to power but but also likes
to remind his audience whether it's
students or broader than that what what
is you know what is it what is the life
well a good life well lived and now
there I think there are there are
problems in how in the age of soundbites
and hundreds of hours of footage and
tons of speaking and those kind of
things that become problematic and I'm
not in any way convinced that if I sat
down with him and said hey mate what
about this bit that he would actually
stand and defend them but impressions I
get would be that his I think he
sometimes over catastrophize is the
slippery slope to Marxism in the sense
of that that all that you know this way
lies Stalinist death camps therefore we
cannot give one inch on on concessions
to progressive idea
although having said that I have also
personally experienced the almost
Chinese Communists like Tom Xing
struggle sessions of political
correctness in in the Academy and its
kind of left-wing you know left coast
idea so it's not that I don't see the
peril I do I just think sometimes he
uses the slippery slope argument maybe I
think it pulls it out just sometimes a
little early is the bottom line without
necessarily enough conditions to justify
it he sometimes in my experience I think
I remember him on Joe Rogan doing the
life is nasty brutish and short the kind
of Hobbesian it's always been this way
therefore any efforts to try and
recalibrate or rebalance the scales are
fundamentally flawed delusional and by
the way lead to the Stalinist death
camps without any more nuanced
socio-political critique of practices
and policies so for instance
concentration of wealth and the 1% and
even the percentage of 1% has been
directly traceable in at least in the US
over you know tax and tax and corporate
law various various deliberate policies
that are fundamentally different in the
70s and 80s and have now resulted in an
incredible skewing an aggregation of
wealth in the hands of the few
for him to skip over that and go to
lobsters and serotonin feels like
skipping some critical steps and also
skipping some critical places of
potential responsibility for me his
success signifies how much we're
thirsting for this father energy in our
culture what do you make of Jordan
Peters and what do you make of the
Jordan Peterson phenomena you know I
think first of all I would not have
predicted it so I don't want to I I
think maybe I'm often called and among
my among my people who agree with me I'm
called a visionary and but I was not a
visionary and for seeing Jordan Peterson
I think it's amazing that an
intellectual that is young in who is you
know who speaks in terms of often of
metaphor and an allegory that he has
risen to such extraordinary success and
I think it is a reason is in part a
result of our enormous
hunger we you know we have we've
attached to two extremely unlikely
figures because it our hunger the Donald
Trump on the one hand and Jordan
Peterson on the other two ends of the
extreme in terms of somebody who's been
willing to say you know fathers are
important families are important and so
Jordan and I found ourselves in in a
hour-and-a-half dialogue in which I
would give a you know I would talk about
fathers and roughhousing and he would
talk about some intellectual Piaget or
someone else who was you know who was in
the literature or in Disney movies or or
is something else that related to that
and it was just a fascinating
hour-and-a-half I I think because you
know I'm usually when I'm being
interviewed I don't learn a great deal
but I certainly learned it was wonderful
the way we learned from each other and
you'll you're from Canada yeah one of
the the the biggest phenomenon of the
last couple of years has been Jordan
Peterson yeah would it be made of him
his rise and what it says about the
culture that people are so thirsting for
what he's talking about
Peterson first was very bright
extraordinaire articulate and in some
ways a compelling speaker so he said
he's an attractive figure in some ways
when I read him I sense a lot of
suppressed rage in him in fact I think
his voice is choking with a rage alot of
time
it's anything as he talks about rage
that you have to deal with it I don't
think you'll understand just how angry
yet and it's and and if you look at his
websites the comments were full of rage
by his young acolytes well that's an
energetic thing that it's his energy
that draws people as much as what he
actually teaches secondly he teaches a
repression I mean he he very rightly
takes an issue where somebody mandates a
second language
very rightly and righteously since the
pie will not be dictated to about what
language I'm gonna use but good for him
I'm all in favor of not mandating
language on the one hand on the other
hand he basically advocates repression
in his book he talks about how an angry
to your child needs to be sit by
themselves until they get over it rather
than understanding why a child would be
angry rage - what frustrations are
having and what human contact they need
to help them move through that anger he
says we press the anger so he's all
about repressed anger for example
circuit and it's very interesting he
talks about children he talks humble
little varmints and little monsters and
so on I know that's meant to be humorous
but it's also certainly you're thinking
of the young human child so
fundamentally I steam as an agent of
repression he posing as an agent of
libertarianism not to mention he's got
this big in his bonnet about what he
considers to be seems to consider to be
conspiracies by left-wing intellectuals
they seem to be his bete noire being a
left-wing intellectual myself I'd like
to talk to him so now what were you so
upset about Jordan were you so afraid of
you know he talks about these bloody
Marxists and and any any points are very
accurately all the horror that occurred
under so-called Marxist regimes
particularly in the Soviet Union
he's absolutely accurate about that but
then he promotes Christianity shall I
tell him about the mass murders that
occurred in the name of Christianity
should I tell him about all the millions
that were slaughtered in the names of
the gentle Jesus in other words let's be
fair about it he seems to pick
ideologies to attack and abhor and
embrace other ideologies that are just
as murderers in practice sometimes it's
a much more interesting question for me
what happened is
how come underneath Arg I was meant to
be liberate people so many people were
oppressed I come from Eastern Europe I
was born in Hungary he doesn't have to
tell me about what was like but how
about asking how come a religious
philosophy that was meant to promote
love and acceptance and compassion has
become such an agent of 2 million a of
repression oppression and
and-and-and-and-and killing so can we be
objective or we're gonna be simply
tribal about it I have a lot to say to
Jordan or a lot to as much as I
appreciate actually some of what he says
and as interesting as I find them I
think is a very mixed figure largely an
occasion to of repression
[Music]